[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Forty-two]
[第四十二集]
Aye! Aye! Aye!
好好好
The food we eat is from those ones work hard in the fields.
我们吃的粮食是那种田的人做的
[Chen Wangdao, Translator of "The Communist Manifesto"]
[陈望道 《共产党宣言》翻译]
Not from the Emperor, the President,
不是皇帝 总统
nor from the bureaucrats.
做官的人做的
The clothes we wear are made by tailors.
我们穿的衣服是裁缝做的
Not by the Emperor,
也不是皇帝 总统
not by the President.
做官的人做的
The houses we live in
我们住的房屋
were made by carpenters and bricklayers.
是木匠 瓦匠 小工做的
Not by the Emperor, the President,
更不是皇帝 总统
nor by the bureaucrats.
做官的人做的
The trains and boats we take
我们坐的各种车船
were made by carpenters, blacksmiths, painters,
是木匠 铁匠 漆匠做的
by many machinists,
还有许多机器匠
operated by boatmen, handcart workers,
驾船工人 掌车工人
by sailers, porters, and others.
水手 搬运工人等等
[Chen Duxiu, courtesy name Zhongfu]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫]
Because of them,
有他们 才能够把我们的货物
we can deliver our goods and we can go to other places.
和我们自己送向远方
These are not the merits of the Emperor, the President
这些都不是皇帝 总统
nor the bureaucrats.
做官的人的功劳
In this world,
这个世界上
if there were no farmers,
若是没有种田的
carpenters, bricklayers, workmen,
裁缝 木匠 瓦匠
blacksmiths, painters, mechanics,
小工 铁匠 漆匠
craftsmen, boatmen, handcart workers,
机器匠 驾船工人 掌车工人
sailors, porters, and others,
水手 搬运工人等
then we would have no food,
那我们便没有饭吃
no clothes, no houses,
没有衣穿 没有房屋住
[Zhao Shiyan, courtesy Qinsheng]
[赵世炎 字 琴生]
no trains, no boats.
没有车坐 没有船坐
So it's clear that only those who work,
如此可见 人类各项人中
among all kinds of men, are pillars of society.
只有做工的人是台柱子
It is their strength
因为有他们的力量
that supports the whole of society.
才能够把整个社会撑住
If there were no workers,
若是没做工的人
then we would have no food, clothing, housing or transportation.
那我们便没有了衣食住和交通
We would not survive.
我们便不能生存
If so,
如此
wouldn't the society collapse into nothing?
人类的社会岂不是要倒塌吗
Thus I say, only those who work
我所以说只有做工的人
are the most vital and the most precious!
最有用 最贵重
Aye!
好
Long live the workers!
劳工万岁
[Changxindian, Beijing]
[北京长辛店]
Workers and friends,
广大的工人朋友们
This issue of "New Youth"
这一期的《新青年》
introduces in detail
详细地介绍了
the origin and significance of the May 1st International Labor Day.
五一国际劳动节的由来还有意义
Moreover, a big part in this issue
而且用了大量的篇幅
was devoted to introducing the fight and life
介绍了我们中国工人阶级的斗争
of our Chinese working class.
和生活的情况
I suggest
我建议啊
that we should talk in depth about it
我们长辛店的工人夜校
in this evening school for Changxindian workers,
要好好地宣传一下这个情况
so as to organize the mass working class.
好把广大的工人阶级都组织起来
[Li Dazhao, courtesy name Shouchang, Director of Peking University Library]
[李大钊 字 守常 北京大学图书馆主任]
Is that okay?
好不好
Aye!
好
Everybody, please be quiet.
大家安静一下
Mr. Dazhao,
大钊先生
please tell us more about it.
您现在就给我们讲讲吧
Let's  welcome
我们大家欢迎
Mr. Dazhao to give us a speech.
大钊先生给我们演讲
Aye!
好
Sure, how about I talk about the origin of the May 1st International Labor Day?
好 那么我就给大家讲一讲
You fine with that?
五一国际劳动节的由来 好不好
Yes!
好
May 1st, 1886
一八八六年的五月一号
350,000 labor workers
美国两万个企业的
from 20,000 American companies
三十五万名劳工
went on strike.
停工 罢工
They all flocked to the street
他们都涌到了大街上
and held a massive demonstration.
举行了声势浩大的示威活动
What for?
示威什么呢
They demonstrated to the government,
他们向政府示威
requesting for a better life condition
要求改善他们生活
and also working conditions.
和工作的条件
They asked to work only eight hours a day.
他们要求每天只工作八小时
They sang "Eight Hours Song".
而且他们唱着《八小时之歌》
The lyrics are quite interesting.
这个歌词特别地有意思
Let me tell you about it, okay?
我给大家说一说好不好
Yes!
好
The lyrics go like this.
歌词大意是这样的
"We meant to make things over,"
我们要改变这个世界
"We are tired"
我们已经厌倦了
"We are tired of toil for naught"
每天白白地辛劳
"With but bare enough to live upon"
才只能挣到这么一点糊口的工钱
"We want eight hours a day"
我们要每天工作八小时
"As we have ne'er an hour for thought."
因为 我们没有时间思考了
"We should have the eight hour work day"
我们要实行八小时工作制
"We want to smell the flow'rs"
我们要闻闻花香
"And we want to feel the sunshine"
我们要晒晒太阳
"We are sure that God has willed it"
因为我们相信
"And we mean to have eight hours;"
上帝只让我们工作八小时
"From the shipyard, shop and mill"
我们从船坞 车间 工厂
"We're summoning our forces"
召集了我们的队伍
"Eight hours for work,"
我们争取八小时工作
"Eight hours for rest"
八小时休息
"Eight hours for what we will!"
另外的八小时 留给我们自己
Aye! Aye! Aye!
好 好 好
Shizhi, you waiting for me?
适之 等我呢
Tell me, is this still the "New Youth"
这还是我们北大同人
edited by us Peking University colleagues?
编辑的《新青年》吗
The "New Youth" now
这样的《新青年》
is it still a magazine of enlightenment?
还是思想启蒙的杂志吗
Zhongfu, what is it he wants?
仲甫他想干什么
What's wrong here?
怎么了
The New Youth!
堂堂 《新青年》
Made a special issue for illiterate workers.
为不识字的工人做了一期专刊
See what it's written inside!
里面讲的竟然全是
Casual daily chores about merely household stuff!
柴米油盐酱醋茶的事情
The New Youth!
堂堂 《新青年》
Do we not care about academic level anymore?
还讲不讲究学术品位了
Shizhi, didn't we all agree?
适之 咱们不是说好了吗
How to run "New Youth" is Brother Zhongfu's business.
《新青年》 交给仲兄去办
We are only responsible for writing.
咱们只负责写稿
As for what it will be.
至于办成什么样
That's his decision.
那是他的事
His decision?
他的事
Wrong!
不对
New youth
《新青年》
It's Li Dazhao's New Youth.
是你李大钊的 《新青年》
It's me, Hu Shi's New Youth.
是我胡适的《新青年》
It's everyone's New Youth.
是大家的《新青年》
Do you think this is all right?
你觉得这样办行吗
I think it's good.
我觉得这么办挺好
I heard that the sales of this issue is doing well too.
听说这一期的销量也很好
I'm done talking to you.
我不跟你说了
I'm going to write to Zhongfu.
我这就去给仲甫写信
No way I would allow Chen Zhongfu
我绝对不允许陈仲甫
tarnish "New Youth" like this!
这样糟踢《新青年》
Come on, come on, come on
来来来来
Come in, Runzhi.
润之进来
Sir.
先生
Took you time.
怎么才来啊
Didn't you leave Beijing long ago?
你不是早就离开北京了吗
What's this?
这是什么
Here are some peanuts and jujubes.
这是一些花生和大枣
I passed Shandong on the way.
我 路过山东
Brought you some local specialties.
给您带了点特产
After leaving Beijing
从北京离开之后
I went down south.
我就一路南下
I climbed Mount Tai and visited Confucius Temple.
去爬了泰山 拜了孔庙
I had a good journey and leart a lot.
到处看看 收获颜丰
I arrived in Shanghai last night.
这昨天晚上才到了上海
First thing today I came here.
今天就急着来见您了
You went to Qufu.
你去了曲阜了
Yes.
对
I went to see the old residence of Confucius and his cemetery.
我去看了孔子的故居还有墓地
And burned incense stick too.
还给老夫子烧了香呢
I would have asked you to do the same thing on my behalf.
早知道就请你代我也烧一灶香
So to ask Confucius to cut me some slack.
让老夫子不要骂我陈独秀
And to critisize Yuan Shikai instead of me.
要骂 骂袁世凯
He restored the monarchy in the name of Confucius,
是他假用老夫子的帽子复辟帝制
had the whole nation condemning him.
这样才天下共讨之
Isn't it?
对吧
To be honest.
其实说心里话
I do admire Confucius
我陈独秀骨子里
from the bottom of my heart.
倒是挺崇拜老夫子的
If there is a chance
假若有机会
I'll also go to Qufu to burn a incense stick to pay my respect.
我也去趟曲阜 给他上灶香
Sir.
先生
I think Confucius wouldn't mind you do so.
我认为老夫子是不会见怪的
Because he understands,
因为他心里知道
that he is just a portrait now.
他呢只是一个画像
As for how to paint it, it's a matter for future generations.
至于怎么贴那是后人的事
That's a good point.
这话说得好
Runzhi.
润之啊
You are one of the few wise men.
你是少有的明白人
By the way, how is the anti-Zhang movement going?
对了 驱张运动进展如何
I wrote something the end of last year
去年年底我在《新青年》
on New Youth,
还发表了一篇
"Welcome Hunan People's Spirit"
《欢迎湖南人底精神》
so to support you guys.
来声援你们
Yes, I've wanted to thank you for a long time
是啊 我早就想来谢谢您了
Those legit stuggles we did in Beijing,
在京合法抗争
all the peaceful petitions we had,
和平地请愿了七八次
they all failed.
结果都失败了
Now, with warlords at each others' throats,
眼下利用军阀纷争
we might can take this chance and finally put an end to Zhang's cruelty.
有望结束张毒的战害
But after we get rid of Zhang JIngyao,
但是把张敬尧赶走之后
how we should do with the autonomy in Hunan？
湖南自治之路怎么走
I have no clue about it.
我这心里呀 很是困惑
Here is my view.
我告诉你
As long as we have the so-called supervisor general system,
督军制度不除
this world will be still under control of those ones who only know how to shoot guns.
就还是武人的天下
We call it democratic republic,
所谓的民主共和
whilst in fact it is warlords taking turns showing their power,
竟是这类军阀轮流坐庄
stealing from the people and betraying this country.
残民卖国
You want to talk petition, improve people's livelihood
你跟他们上请愿书
and better system with them?
讲改良 讲民生
You might well ask a tiger for its skin.
岂不是与虎谋皮
Sir, you are absolutely right.
先生说得极是
This country is sick in it's bones.
国事沉疯不起
I don't know which medicine is the right one,
到底何为救国之良药
but even with the slightest hope, I will try them all
我都想试试
Though the efforts needed is tremendous.
可是皮费思量
I have always thought it's okay if we do it slowly,
我原来也一直想慢慢调理
with enlightenment education, awakening Chinese people gradually.
启蒙教育 唤醒国人
Step by step.
渐次加以改良
But now there is no time.
但当今无时日
Inside we have warlords, outside we have foreign enemies.
军阀列强内欺外压
If we do it slowly,
如果行动慢了
China will be split apart before we realize it,
中国必将瓜分豆部
we will always be under their fingers.
永远为人鱼肉
The core to save our nation,
救国要义
I think it is to take action immediately.
我看在于立刻唤起行动
Sir.
先生
Then, in your opinion,
那依您看
what kind of ideology is the guideline to save the nation?
何种信仰才是救国行动之指南呢
Marx and Lenin showed us the way.
走马克思 列宁指的路
Take a look.
你看
Chen Wangdao finished this just now.
这是陈望道
The translated full version
刚刚翻译出来的
of The Communist Manifesto.
《共产党宣言》全本
This is the guideline of salvation.
这是救世的经典
I'm doing the proofread so it can be published as soon as possible.
我正在抓紧校阅 准备公开发表
A fully translated Communist Manifesto?
《共产党宣言》 出全译本啦
What I read in Beijing before were all only paragraphs.
我之前在北京看的都是节译本
I've never read the full thing.
不全 一段一段的
Sir.
先生
Can I read it first?
这能不能先给我看看
Of course, not only that.
当然 不仅可以给你看
Runzhi
润之
I wish you could join me.
我还希望你能跟我一样
I wish you could also be a believer in the Communist Party.
能成为共产党的信徒
I think I will.
我想我一定会的
Before I only read some paragraphs,
虽然之前
but those alone
看的只是些节选
has made my heart pounding so hard.
但是我的心哪 早就热血沸腾了
Good.
好
Here, Runzhi.
来润之
Don't go anywhere today.
今天 哪儿都别去
Stay here.
就在我这几
You can finish reading it in one go!
我一口气让你看完
Yes, please.
好请
Members of our Marxist Research Association
我们马克思主义研究会成员
are from three organizations.
来自三个组织
New Youth magazine,
《新青年》 杂志
Weekly Review magazine,
《星期评论》 杂志
and the Current Affairs News.
和《时事新报》
Today, we are have a seminar.
今天 我们开一个讨论会
Everyone knows,
大家都知道
not long ago,
前段时间
Voitinsky from Communist International came to China.
共产国际的维经斯基来到中国
I have met him.
我们也见了面
Voitinsky stayed in China for more than a month.
维经斯基在中国待了一个多月
In Beijing, Tianjin, Shanghai, Jinan and other places
在北京 天津 上海 济南等地
he has met many people,
接触了很多人士
also learned a lot about the current situation.
也了解到一些情况
Comrade Zhao Shiyan will share with us about
下面呢 就请赵世炎同志转述一下
Comrade Voitinsky's thoughts and ideas.
维经斯基同志的一些看法
Please feel free to change your ideas.
另外也希望
About the Chinese ideology research and political circle
大家对中国思想界和政治界
if anyone is keen to discuss,
发表一些看法
discussion is always welcomed.
欢迎讨论
Here are some Comrade Voitinsky's opinions.
维经斯基同志认为
The tide of new culture movement in China is surging unstoppably,
中国关于新思想的潮流虽然澎湃
but first, the contents is too complicated.
但是第一 太复杂
There is anarchism,
有无政府主义
unionism,
有工团主义
socialism,
有社会主义
Kilt socialism.
有基尔特社会主义
All kinds of theory going around without a dominant one.
五花八门 没有一个主流
This kind of chaotic situation
这会使我们的思想
is not helping us to reach a common idea.
陷入混乱的局面
Second, there is no organization.
第二 没有组织
We have too many people with too many empty talk.
做文章 讲空话的人比比皆是
What about the actual action though?
实际行动呢
This is in no way beneficial in starting a revolution in this country.
这绝不利于我国进行革命
So he believes that
所以他认为
the most urgent task
中国的思想界和政治界
for the Chinese ideology research and political circle
最迫切的任务
is to build as soon as possible,
就是尽快建立一个
one firm and strong
坚定的 坚强的
Marxist political party.
马克思主义政党
I don't agree with Voitinsky.
我不同意维经斯基的看法
He doesn't know China at all.
他根本不了解中国
There are too many political parties and factions in China now.
中国现在政党林立 派系严重
There is no point forming a small party now at all.
根本不必成立什么小党
It's not going to work.
这是起不到什么作用的
I think
我认为
Comrade Voitinsky's opinion makes sense.
维经斯基同志的意见是对的
Without the strong leadership of a proletarian party
没有一个无产阶级政党的领导
China can't form a united force now.
中国 终究还是一盘散沙
I have always thought that
各位 我一向认为
China's top priority is to develop industry.
中国的当务之急就是要开发实业
We must first utilise capitalism,
先要发展资本主义
then we will work to achieve socialism.
然后再搞社会主义
Following the path and direction of Russia right now
现在效仿俄国的道路跟方向
will be unrealistic.
那是不现实的
Comrades
各位同志
I think it is urgent for China to build a political party.
我认为中国建党刻不容缓
I agree.
支持
Watch it.
看着点
I'm sorry
不好意思啊
Runzhi
润之同学啊
I have successfully completed the task you gave me.
你交给我的任务我圆满完成了
Shanghai celebrities from all walks of life
上海各界名流
are all very supportive of work-studying in France.
对留法勤工俭学非常地支持
They also cares a lot about Hunan's reform movement.
对湖南改造运动也关爱有加
Everyone took part in donation.
大家蹦跃捐款
20,000 silver dollars was quickly raised.
很快就筹集到了两万银圆
How about that.
怎么样
You didn't come all the way here for nothing.
不你大老远地跑来一趟吧
Twenty thousand silver dollar.
两万银圆
So many.
这么多
Mr. Zhang, thank you very much.
章先生大谢您了
The money came just in time.
这笔钱来得太及时了
When the revolution is successful, we will pay it back.
等革命成功了 我们一定还上
Revolution?
革命
Revolution, huh?
革命啊
What kind of revolution are you talking about?
你说的是哪一种革命啊
Socialist revolution, of course.
当然是社会主义革命
Can it be done in China?
在中国 能成吗
It's too difficult.
太难了吧
Nevertheless, we must overcome many difficulties.
当然要过五关斩六将
Risks and dangers right ahead waiting,
所以履险蹈危 十荡十决
I am still taking this path.
吾往矣
Well-said. Can I live to see it?
好气魄 我能看到吗
You can see it. Trust me.
您一定能看到 相信我
We revolutionary,
革命者
we keep our word and our deeds.
言必信 行必果
Me, Mao Zedong honor my word.
我毛泽东说话算数
Fine, I will be waiting for you to pay back the money.
我等着你还这笔钱
Mrs. Chen, that's enough. There's too much to take.
师母 够了 太多了拿不了
Nonsense, it's a long way to France.
不多 去法国路那么远
You can have it all on the way.
在路上能吃完的
Those are all specialties.
那些都是些特产
You won't be able to find them when you are in France.
去了法国你们也都吃不着的
Exactly, it's too far away.
是啊 路上那么远
And it's hot.
而且天又热
I'm afraid these will go bad.
我怕这些放不住
Shiyan
世炎
You are going to France now.
你这次去法国
In addition to work-study programs
除了勤工俭学之外
there is another important task for you.
还有一个重要的任务
That is to actively promote and learn more about Marxism
那就是在留法勤工俭学学生中
among those other students in France.
去积极地宣传和研究马克思主义
Prepare for the establishment of our organization.
为筹建党小组做准备
I will write to you often too.
我也会多给你写信的
Besides, please.
另外也拜托你
Visit Yannian and Qiaonian more.
常去看看延年 乔年他们两个
The situation of work-study program in France is very complicated.
在法国的勤工俭学的情况很复杂
Yannian can get stubborn sometime.
延年喜欢钻牛角尖
I worry about him.
我还是很担心他的
These are some Chinese materials
这是我给他们准备的
I prepared for them.
一些中文资料
You take it with you.
你带着它
You tell them
你告诉他们
I won't be able to die in peace
如果他们两个不相信马克思主义
if they dont believe in Marxism.
我到死都不会甘心的
Leave it to me.
我一定带到
Don't worry.
放心吧
I've sealed it tight for you.
我都给你们封得可严实了
It will be finr
不会坏的
Haiwei
海威
Mrs. Chen.
师母
Now you are all leaving,
这一去法国
I don't know when I will see you again.
也不知道什么时候才能回来了
Bai Lan, we'll entrust her to you.
白兰 我们就托付给你了
Be sure to take care of her.
一定要好好待她
Mrs.Chen, rest assured.
师母放心
When we are in France,
到了法国
I will do my best.
我一定会好好照顾白兰的
Sister Bai lan.
白兰姐姐
Brother Yannian gave it to me.
这是延年哥哥送我的
Take it with you, it can keep you company on the way.
你带去在路上可以给你陪个伴
Zi mei, I won't take Yingying with me this time.
子美 姐姐就不带英英了
That's because
因为姐姐这次啊
I'm going on a long journey,
路程特别远
and it's by boat.
而且还要坐船
I'm afraid Yingying won't like it.
我怕英英不适应
Okay, but Sister Bai Lan
那白兰姐姐
you need to tell
你一定要告诉
Brother Yannian and Qiaonian that
延年哥哥和乔年哥哥
Mom, dad, little brother and I
爸爸 妈妈 弟弟和我
we miss them very much.
都很想他们
Okay, I will.
好我知道了
All done, time to go.
好了 该走了
It's getting late. Don't miss the boat.
时间不早了 别误了船
Put it back and feed it some water.
乖 放回去 给它喂点水
Grab your stuff.
拿得了啊
Let's go.
走
Shouchang, work for building our party is under way.
守常 建党工作正在抓紧进行
Communist international urges east Asia secretariat
共产国际指示东亚书记处
to hurry on the process of setting up the organization in China.
抓紧帮助中国成立党组织
Comrade Lenin
列宁同志
Comrade Trotsky
托洛茨基同志
And Comrade Stalin.
还有斯大林同志
Are very concerned about China's situation.
都很关心中国问题
We plan to set up the party's initiating group in advance in August.
我们拟于八月先期成立党的发起小组
So we can provide an example for other places.
以为各地榜样
Currently I'm working on draw up a draft
我现在准备草拟一个简单的
of the party's temporary program.
党的临时纲领
I share it with you now so we can have some discussion and modification.
先拿出来 供大家探讨修改
As for the name of this party.
我们的党叫什么名称
It's still uncertain.
尚不好定夺
Some people want to call it the Socialist Party.
有人主张叫社会党
Some the Social Communist Party.
有人主张叫社会共产党
Also some the Social Democratic Party.
有人主张叫社会民主党
Many options.
不一而足
How should we call it?
究竟叫什么党
I'd like to hear your opinion.
我很想听听你的意见
Brother Zhongfu, I have received your letter.
仲甫兄 来信收悉
We here in Beijing
北京的建党工作
are working nonstoppedly as I'm writing this letter right now.
也正在抓紧进行
We plan to hold work with the Chinese Youth Society,
近期拟联合少年中国学会
the Twilight Group, the Humanity Club, the Youth Mutual Aid Group
曙光社 人道社 青年互助团
and Tianjin Awakeness Society, etc.
以及天津觉悟社等
to hold a symposium together in the near future
召开一个座谈会
where commonly-concerned issues will be discussed.
商讨相关问题
We are eager to see the establishment of the party's initiating group
我们迫切盼望上海党的发起组
takes place in Shanghai as soon as possible.
及早成立
So that it can be an example for all of us.
做出样板
As for the name of the party
至于党的名称
I firmly believe that
我坚定地认为
it should be the Communist Party of China（CPC）.
应该叫中国共产党
come on
来来来
Come, Runzhi.
润之来
Yes.
好
Come here.
过来过来
Come and sit.
来 过来坐
Thank you, sir
先生请
You been busy recently?
你最近忙什么
Haven't seen you in a long timw.
怎没见你来啊
Me and some classmates from Hunan First Normal University
我和湖南一师的几个同学
rented places in Minxiang South.
在民巷南里租了几间房
We are having a trial run with work-study life.
试验搞工读生活
It's been a month so far.
搞了一个多月
It's really hard.
苦得很哪
Work-study is not easy.
工读可不容易
Chen Yannian did experiments for two months.
当时陈延年做了两个月实验
Failed
失败了
Then I heard that
后来我听说
Wang Guangqi had a large-scale one,
王光祈搞了个大规模的
also failed.
也失败了
What about you?
你呢
We are engaged in a small experiment of several people.
我们搞的是几个人的小试验
You probably have guessed the result.
不用说就知道结果
You failed too.
也失败了
Yes.
是
But sir
不过先生
I've made my decision now.
我现在已经决定了
I will stop going to school from now on.
我以后再也不进学校了
I want to focus on independent research.
我要走自主研究这条路
Good.
好
Sir
先生
Manifesto of the Communist Party
《共产党宣言》
I carefully read it over and over again.
我认认真真地反复读了几次
I can confirm now that
我现在确定了
I believe in Marxism.
我要信仰马克思主义
For sure?
你真的确信
Sir
先生
Once my faith is established
我的信仰一旦确立了
it will not waver.
就不会动摇
I will fight to the end to achieve communism.
我要为了实现共产主义奋斗到底
Good
好
Runzhi
润之
That's the kind of decision you need.
就需要这样的决断
I'm very happy to hear that
我真的太高兴了
you want to join us.
你能加入我们
From this moment we are comrades.
从此我们就是同志了
Sir
先生
What is the name of our party?
我们的党叫什么名字
Communist Party of China
中国共产党
good
好
That's a great name.
响亮的名字
In ancient times,
昔者
Gonggong's rage collapsed the Mt. Bu Zhou.
共工怒而触不周之山
Sky falling down and the ground tearing apart.
天柱折 地维绝
As the sky twisted and tilted,
天倾西北
the sun, moon and stars all changed their places.
故日月星辰移煮
The ground could no longer cover what's beneath the soil.
地不满东南
This is an ancient Chinese myth.
这是中国的上古神话
There are also many heroes in western mythology.
西方的神话里面也有不少英雄
We will be the Prometheus in China.
我们就要做中国的普罗米修斯
Dare to steal fire without fear of punishment.
不怕天罚 敢于盗火
Hold that fire to light up the future for our nation.
为苦难的中国照亮前程
We also need to prepare ourselves
我们也要准备
for we are determined to crash this old society completely
做共工这样的万死不辞
even if we need to scarifice our lives like what Gonggong did.
勇于彻底粉碎旧社会的猛士
Sir.
先生
I'm going back to Hunan in a few days.
过几天我准备回趟湖南
As for what I should do after I go back,
回去之后要干点什么
I want to hear your opinion.
我想听听您的意见
Runzhi
润之
You know I've always had high hopes for you.
你知道我一直对你寄予厚望
This time,
你这次回去
please actively promote Marxism,
要积极地宣传马克思主义
mobilize the people,
发动民众
prepare for the establishment of the Party organization in Hunan.
为筹建在湖南的党组织做好准备
I'll take your advice, Sir
好 我听先生的
I will keep contacting you,
我会多跟你联系
writing you letters.
给你写信
I will write to you, too.
我也会给您写信的
Many years later
许多年后
Mao Zedong recalled.
毛泽东回忆说
"It is probably for the conversation with Chen Duxiu as he firmly stated his belief
在我一生中
at a very critical period
可能是关键性的这个时期
in my life,
陈独秀表明自己信仰的那些话
that has left a deep impression on me."
给我留下了深刻的印象
He also said
他还说
"There was this magazine called New Youth.
那个时候有《新青年》 杂志
It was edited by Chen Duxiu.
是陈独秀主编的
Those people who were waken up by this magazine
被这个杂志
and the May Fourth Movement.
和五四运动警醒起来的人
Later, some joined the Communist Party.
后来有一部分进了共产党
These people were affected by Chen Duxiu
这些人受陈独秀
and the group of people around him.
和他周围一群人的影响很大
It's fair to say that Chen Duxiu was the one gathered all those people,
可以说是由他集合起来
which eventually leaded to the establishment of the party."
这才成立了党
Comrades, today's meeting
同志们 今天这个会议
It was proposed by Comrade En Lai.
是恩来同志提议召开的
Their ideas of joint-work and transformation
他们关于各个先进组织
about pioneer organizations are worth to listen to.
联合和改造的创意 很好
So I propose comrades from Tianjin Awaken Club
所以我提议今天这个会议
shuold take the role as the host
由天津觉悟社的同志
and to give general report at today's meeting.
主持并且作总报告
Is that okay?
大家觉得怎么样
Yes, comrade, please.
恩来同志 请
Since Mr. Li Dazhao named me,
既然李大钊先生点了我的将
I will take the job with gratitude.
那我就不客气了
I think
我认为
for us youth gather under the red banner of reformation
我们集合在
we must come together for all the people,
改造赤旗下的青年同志
create a union that breaks all boundaries
认当今的人类
and based on the spirit of love and mutual assistance.
必须基于相爱互助的精神
In this alliance
在这个联合里
the life of each and everyone
各分子的生活
must be free and equal,
必须是自由的 平等的
Industrious and happy.
勤劳且幸福的
To realize such a harmonious world,
要想实现这样一个大同的世界
to bring the life of great unity of mankind,
人类大联合的生活
we must start with free the people.
不可不先由自由人民
The foundation will be different groups
按他们的职业
based on people's occupation.
结合的小组织为基础
We have to merge ourselves
我们为渴望各种组织
with the common people.
一个个地实现
We have to make our voices heard to all walks of life,
不能不奔走相告
so that what we want can come true.
高呼着到民间去
Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生
Please share your thoughts with us.
您再给我们来说说吧
Comrades, just now, Comrade Enlai gave us a speech.
同志们 刚才恩来同志的演讲
Everyone heard it.
大家都听到了
Wonderful.
非常地精彩
Now all walks of life in the country
现在全国各界
especially the workers' movement has already started.
尤其是工人运动都已经搞起来了
Indeed it's time that all our pioneer organizations
那么各个先进组织
need to work together and to change and improve
确实需要联合 需要改造
to strengthen oursleves.
以壮大我们自身的力量
But all that has a common premise.
但是联合和改造需要有一个前提
About which,
这个问题
everyone needs to have a correct understanding.
大家应该要有一个正确的认识
I think it is vital for all organizations
我认为 各个先进组织
to clearly indicate their program and guideline.
首先要有标明自己主义之必要
Unidentified doctrine
主义不明
means no scientific guiding ideology.
便没有一个科学的指导思想
Internally, it is not enough to unify our members.
对内既不足以齐一全体之心志
Externally, it is not enough to unite with other people's actions.
对外尤不足以联合他人之行动
Comrades, the time has come now,
同志们 当今中国
our organization must raise our own banner
已经到了我们这个组织
showing it to this nation.
举起自己大旗的时候了
Comrades
同志们
Before the official establishment of the party organization,
今天在成立党组织之前
I want to read this out first.
我想先宣读一下
I drafted a provisional program of the party.
我草拟的一个党的临时纲领
Main contents can be divided into party principles
主要分为党的原则
and the purpose of the party.
和党的目的两部分
There are three principles of the Communist Party.
共产党原则 有三条
First, Confiscate all capital.
没收一切资本
Confiscation of bank, mines.
没收银行 矿山
Abolish individual oppression.
废除个人压迫个人
The scoiety shares the economical benefits.
经济上社会共有
Second, leading the working class to power
领导工人阶级获得政权
Down with reactionary forces
打倒反动势力
Transition to the elimination of political power
过渡到消灭政权
Third, eliminate existences of classes.
三消灭一切阶级
There are also three purposes of the Communist Party.
共产党的目的也有三条
First, to carry out class struggle.
要进行阶级斗争
Unite workers.
团结工人
Eventually move from economic struggle to political struggle.
由经济争斗发展到政治争斗
Seize political power.
夺取政权
Second,
取得政权以后
carry out class struggle.
发展阶级争斗
Build a communist society
建设共产主义社会
based on mass production.
以大规模生产为基础
If noone is against what I said,
大家要是没什么意见
please approve by applause.
请鼓掌通过
Comrades
同志们
According to the Communist Party of China（CPC）'s organizational principles
根据中国共产党的组织原则
We elect Comrade Chen Duxiu
我们选举陈独秀同志
to be Secretary of the Executive Board of the Communist Party of China（CPC）.
为中国共产党执行局书记
goodGood.
好
Comrades
同志们
From now on,
从现在起
we are the first members
我们几个就是共产党的
of the Communist Party.
第一批党员了
As of today, the Chinese working class
从今天起 中国的工人阶级
has its own vanguard party.
就有了自己的先锋队组织
It's name is the Communist Party of China.
我们的名字叫中国共产党
Now, we take the oath.
现在 我们宣誓
[August 1920, the first branch of the Communist Party of China was established in Shanghai]
1920年8月, 中国共产党第一个期组织在上海成立
Chen Duxiu
陈独秀
Li Hanjun
李汉俊
Yu Xiusong
俞秀松
Shi Cuntong
施存统
Chen Gongpei
陈公培
It is my will to join the Communist Party of China,
志愿加入中国共产党
and fight for communism throughout my life.
决心为共产主义奋斗终生
Long live the Communist Party of China!
中国共产党方岁
Today, the Beijing branch of the Communist Party of China
今天 中国共产党北京小组
is established.
正式成立了
The three of us
我们三人
are fortunate to be the first party members of the branch.
有幸成为小组的第一批党员
Next, we take the oath.
接下来 我们宣誓
Li Dazhao
李大钊
Zhang Shenfu
张申府
Zhang Guotai
张国泰
It is my will to join the Communist Party of China,
志愿加入中国共产党
and fight for communism throughout my life.
决心为共产主义奋斗终生
Comrades, let's cheer.
同志们 让我们高呼
Long live the Communist Party of China!
中国共产党万岁
November 1920
一九二〇年十一月
The Hunan self-governmence movement
毛泽东领导的
with peaceful petition as it's main method
以和平请愿为主要方式的
leaded by Mao Zedong
湖南自治运动
failed.
失败了
Disappointed by which,
失望之余
he went to Pingxiang, Jiangxi
他来到江西萍乡
to investigate about the underclass,
深入考察社会底层
especially the Anyuan coal miners' living conditions
特别是安源煤矿工人的生活状况
and political demands.
和政治诉求
The facts and lessons learnt through it
事实和教训
made him completely giveing up on
使他彻底摆脱了
the last piece of fantasy he had towards the road of reformism.
对社会改良道路的最后一丝幻想
Without hesitation,
义无反顾地
he embarked on the revolutionary road of thoroughly transforming society
走上了彻底改造社会的革命道路
and became a staunch Marxist.
成为一名坚定的马克思主义者
Runzhi
文具
You're back.
你回来了
What did you get from your trip to Pingxiang?
萍乡之行 有什么收获
It's a hard journey, it changed me.
思想苦旅 洗心革面
Feels like a phoenix,
凤凰馨
rebirth from the fire.
浴火重生呗
Well
你看
That sounds serious.
这么严肃
No wonder we were called here early in the morning.
怪不得一大早把我们叫来
What's the matter?
有什么要紧事
There is a fire in my heart.
我这心里呀 有一团火
I want to talk to you two about it.
想找你俩聊聊
What is this fire.
你有什么火
Just tell us.
别着 说出来
This time I went to Pingxiang,
我这次去萍乡
mainly to learn more about the situations there
主要就是想了解煤矿
in rural areas and in mines.
和农村的情况
China now
现在的中国
the whole thing is like a big stove.
整个就像个大火炉
The common people are in dire straits and suffering greatly.
这老百姓水深火热 灾难深重
It's like they are pushed towards death every second.
简直是活不下去了
Tell us what you saw.
你跟我们说说你看到的情况
Take Anyuan Coal Mine for example.
就拿安源煤矿来说
There are many coal diggers there.
那里有好多的挖煤工
They all have to work under the whip of the supervisor.
他们都要在监工的皮鞭下工作
The working conditions are extremely bad.
这劳动的条件恶劣到了极致
Everyday, they have to work twelve to sixteen hours.
每天都要工作十二到十六个小时
They created so much wealth,
创造了这么大的财富
yet their wages are pitiful.
可他们的工资呢却少得可怜
The miners have to live in shacks.
这矿工们都要住在窝棚里
It's freezing cold in winter.
这一到了冬天 简直冷得要命
The situation in the countryside
这农村的情况
is even worse.
就更糟糕了
Beggars, refugees,
这逃荒要饭的
children and female being sold everywhere.
卖儿卖女的到哪儿都是
This country is rotten to the core.
这个国家已经烂透了
What do you think?
你怎么想的
I have figured it out.
我已经想明白了
Just like what Chen Duxiu
像陈独秀
and Mr. Li Dazhao said,
李大钊先生说的那样
we are going to take the road Russian did,
我们要走俄国的道路
to thoroughly transform the whole society
要对整个社会进行彻底地改造
so this country can be saved.
才有可能挽救中国
If we want to save China,
若想救中国
there's only one way.
那出路只有一条
Revolution.
革命
The world is our world
天下者 我们的天下
The country, our country
国家者 我们的国家
Society, our society
社会者 我们的社会
If we don't speak up, who will?
我们不说 谁说
If we don't take actions, who will?
我们不干 谁干
Comrades
同志们
Today is a particularly memorable day.
今天是一个特别值得纪念的日子
The Changsha group of the Communist Party of China（CPC）is formally established.
中国共产党长沙小组正式成立
Comrade Chen Duxiu, secretary of the Communist Party of China（CPC）
中国共产党书记陈独秀同志
needs to go to Guangdong
因为要到广东去
to take office as chairman of the Education Committee.
就任教育委员会委员长
So he can't attend
就不能参加
the founding ceremony of Changsha Group.
长沙小组的成立仪式了
He entrusted me to host it.
他委托我来主持
In view of the current situation,
鉴于目前的形势
this matter can't be made public yet
这件事情还不能公开
We should carry out activities in secret.
我们要采取秘密的形式开展活动
As for now,
现在
our main tasks are as follows.
我们的主要工作有两项
The first is to transform Xinmin Academic Group.
第一是改造新民学会
Make it a party organization.
使之成为党的组织
The second is to establish Hunan Socialist Youth League.
第二是创建湖南社会主义青年团
Now
现在
Let's raise our fists.
让我们举起拳头
Let's say it gently but firmly,
轻轻地呼喊
Long live the Communist Party of China.
中国共产党方岁
Mr. Songnian
崧年先生
This is my notes on studying Mraxist works
这是我来欧洲以后
and some thoughts
学习马克思主义著作的笔记
after I came to Europe.
和思想心得
I am willing to accept the organization's inspection.
我愿意接受组织的考察
Come and sit down, comrade Enlai.
恩来同志 坐
I know about your situation in the past.
你过去的情况我了解
I want to know about
我想听听
changes in your mind since you came to Europe.
你来欧洲之后的思想变化
I arrived in Europe at the end of last year.
我是去年年底到的欧洲
I lived in England for more than a month,
先在英国住了一个多月
spent that time inspecting the workers' movement in Britain.
主要是考察英国的工人运动
Through this investigation and research
通过这种考察和研究
it helped with mine understanding of several popular doctrines in Europe.
帮助我对欧洲流行的几种主义
I made my own deduction and comparison,
进行了推求和比较
reached my final determination.
最终认定
British Fabian socialism is mere fantasy.
英国式的费边社会主义还是空想
Russia's October Revolution is the correvt road.
俄国十月革命的道路才是正确的
How many Marx's books have you read
那到了欧洲之后
after you came to Europe?
你读了多少马克思的书
When I was studying in Japan
我在日本留学的时候
I have been exposed to Marxism.
就接触过马克思主义
Back in China,
在国内
I have read some books on Marxism
又在李大钊先生那里
borrowed from Mr. Li Dazhao.
看过一些马克思主义的读物
After coming to Europe.
来到欧洲之后呢
I read systematically again on
我又系统地阅读了
Manifesto of the Communist Party,
《共产党宣言》
Socialism from Utopia to Science,
《社会主义从空想到科学》
State and Revolution
《国家与革命》等
and other classic works of Marxism.
马克思主义经典著作
I have written everything I learnt in this notebook.
这本笔记记录了我的心得
Now I'm sure
现在我确信
I have established the belief of communism.
我已经树立了共产主义的信念
So I asked to join the Communist Party of China（CPC）.
所以我要求加入中国共产党
Comrade Enlai
恩来同志
I can see how you have come a long way.
你现在的情况我也很了解了
Before I came to Europe,
在我来欧洲之前呢
Comrade Chen Duxiu and Li Dazhao
陈独秀和季大钊同志
entrusted Zhao Shiyan and me
委托我和赵世炎
to be responsible for the formation of the Communist Party of China（CPC）
负责组建中国共产党
Communist group in France.
旅法共产主义小组
And give us the power to develop Party members.
并且授予我们发展党员的权力
Me and Qingyang,
我和清扬呢
we are very willing to be your sponsor.
非常愿意做你的入党介绍人
Shiyan and I have sent a letter to Mr. Zhongfu
具体情况我已经和世炎
about the specific situation.
去信跟仲甫先生汇报了
Now it's only his reply we needed.
现在就等他的回复了
Yes.
好
At the moment,
现在呢
Work-study program is at it's most difficult time.
是勤工俭学最困难的时候
There is huge gaps formed among the students.
留学生的队伍分化很大
We should take the chance, do more work,
我们应该因势利导 多做工作
and unite more comrades
团结更多的同志
to join us.
加入到我们队伍中来
Enlai
恩来
About Chen Yannian and Chen Qiaonian,
陈延年和陈乔年的工作
how's everything going?
做得怎么样了
I discussed it with Shiyan.
我和世炎商量过了
We will go and talk to them together.
一起去做他们两个人的工作
Mr. Song Nian, Enlai.
崧年先生 恩来
Mr. Zhongfu agreed to our party building plan.
仲甫先生同意了我们的建党计划
The France branch of the Communist Party of China has us five members.
要求中国共产党旅法小组
Zhang Shenfu, Zhao Shiyan, Chen Gongpei,
由张申府 赵世炎 陈公培
Liu Qingyang and Zhou Enlai.
刘清扬 周恩来五人组成
He asked us to actively develop more members.
并要求我们积极发展其他党员
That's great, that's great.
太好了 太好了
Now I declare
现在我宣布
the France branch of the Communist Party of China is formally established.
中国共产党旅法小组正式成立了
Long live the Communist Party of China
中国共产党万岁
Since the second half of 1920
从一九二〇年下半年起
Besides Shanghai and Beijing
长
Dong Biwu, Chen Tanqiu, Bao Huiseng and others in Wuhan.
董必武 陈潭秋 包惠僧等在武汉
Wang Jinmei, Deng Engming and others in Jinan.
王尽美 邓恩铭等在济南
Tan Pingshan, Chen Gongbo and others in Guangzhou.
谭平山陈公博等在广州
Mao Zedong, He Shuheng and others in Changsha.
毛泽东 何叔衡等在长沙
Shi Cuntong, Zhou Fohai and others in Japan.
施存统周佛海等在日本
Zhang Shenfu, Zhou Enlai, Zhao Shiyan, Chen Gongpei and others in France.
长申府周恩来赵世炎陈公培等在法
All established Communist Party groups successively.
都先后成立了共产党小组
I'm making an announcement.
宣布几件事情啊
"New Youth", from the eighth issue,
《新青年》 从第八期起
it will change to
实际上就是
an official publication of The Communist Party of China.
中国共产党的机关刊物了
It will no longer adopt the rotating-editor system
不再实行由北京上海同人
by colleagues in Shanghai and Beijing.
轮流编辑的制度
Instead, me and Chen Wangdao,
由我和陈望道
with Lida, Li Hanjun
还有李达 李汉俊
Shen Yanbing will be in charge of editing.
沈雁冰负责编辑
Second, "New Youth" will add two new columns
第二 《新青年》将增加
focusing on Marxist studies
马克思主义研究
and researches in Russia.
两个重点的栏目
At the same time it will continue to take
并同时继续肩负
the important task of propagating new ideas and new cultures.
宣传新思想新文化的重要任务
Third, from this issue
第三 从本期起
the new youth club organized by colleagues in editoral department
编辑部的同人自行组织新青年社
will be directly in charge of the department
直接负责编辑部的
and everything about printing and distribution.
印刷发行的一切事务
The New Youth officially stops cooperating with Qunyi Publication.
正式与群益书社脱离关系
At No.279 Fada Road, French Concession, Shanghai
在上海法租界法大马路279号
a general distribution office will be set up.
设立总经销处
Along with 94 representative offices
并在全国四十三个地区
set up in 43 regions of the country.
设立九十四个代派处
good
好
Great
太好了
This is the cover of the new design of New Youth.
这是 《新青年》 新设计的封面
Please share your opinions.
各位编辑发表意见
Two big hands clasped tightly on the earth.
两只大手在地球上紧紧相握
What does this picture mean?
这个图是什么意思
I guess it indicates the tight unity and relationship
我猜 是预示着中国
between China and Russia
和十月革命后的
after the October Revolution.
俄国的团结合作吧
The Chinese and Russian parties shake hands cordially with each other,
对中俄两党亲切握手
instead hug.
但不是拥抱
In that way,
那这么一来
this picture is very meaningful.
这个图非常有意义呀
Good!
好啊
Comrades, the situation is evloving rapidly now.
同志们 现在形势发展得很快
Study and publicize Marxism,
研究和宣传马克思主义
as for now,
已经是
it's the trend starting a prairie fire in China's ideological circle.
中国思想界的燎原之势
Irresistible and unstoppable.
不可阻挡
But at the same time
但是同时
the groups of the new culture movement is also undergoing fission.
新文化运动的阵营也在发生裂变
What happened?
发生了什么呢
There is a big debate going on now.
发生了关于中国
Should China take the socialist road
是应该走社会主义道路
or the capitalist road?
还是资本主义道路
Shall we choose implementation of social revolution
是实施社会革命
Or social improvement?
还是社会改良的大论战
There is also another big debate
同时还发生了马克思主义
between Marxism and anarchism.
与无政府主义的大论战
Comrades, the two debates
同志们 这两个论战
are gonna deeply influence the future of the Chinese revolution.
关系到中国革命的前途
So I hope
所以我希望
us from Peking University Research Institute of Marxist Theory
我们北京大学马克思学说研究会
and comrades
和即将成立的
from Beijing branch of the Communist Party of China,
中国共产党北京支部的同志们
actively taking parts in the debates.
一定要积极地参加这两个大论战
We need clearly shows our attitudes.
旗帜鲜明地表明我们的态度
New youth
《新青年》
and the upcoming Communist Party magazine
和即将创刊的《共产党》 杂志
will be our battlefield.
就是我们的阵地
Yes.
好